<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ivo Steimanis</title>
    <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://ivosteimanis.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Ivo Steimanis</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/media/icon_hu20ec63765a9f31cb4a6897ee299a78ea_26261_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Ivo Steimanis</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relational values and citizens’ assemblies in the context of adaptation to sea-level rise</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/relational_cosust/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/relational_cosust/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No crowding out among those terminated from an ongoing PES program in Colombia</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/pes_termination/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/pes_termination/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BehaviorChange</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/project/behaviorchange/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/project/behaviorchange/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Landscapes are increasingly dominated by agroforestry, infrastructure and urbanized areas, and wildlife communities are changing dramatically. West African wildlife, including bats, primates, rodents or ungulates host a wide spectrum of pathogens, some of them with zoonotic potential, such as Coronaviruses, Monkeypox and Ebola virus. Some species only remain in marginalized natural habitats, other species thrive and increase in abundance, a situation referred to as post-depletion sustainability. These dynamics have critical consequences of global relevance regarding the reorganization of interactions at the human-wildlife interface and, thus, opportunities for zoonotic disease emergence. Such increasing anthropogenic influences require a shift of thinking from public health towards planetary health, which requires the collaboration of researchers from multiple disciplines and societal stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Habitat co-use and wildlife exploitation (hunting, trading, consuming) take place within a complex social-ecological system (SES) with spatial and temporal variability, social and governance drivers, and multiple-scale processes. Thus, addressing the risks associated with human-wildlife contacts requires transdisciplinary integration of practical and theoretical knowledge to support scientifically valid and socially relevant transformation processes. In terms of ecological factors, higher wildlife host density correlates with the spread of infectious diseases, while outbreak risk in high-biodiversity environments could be lower. Simultaneously, people in the tropics still rely on wild meat as a protein source and build their livelihoods around the wild meat supply chain. Hunting and trading are important for people to earn a living, however, especially in urban areas consumption is not essential. Demand for wild meat has been linked to higher income levels which combined with rapid urbanization threatens biodiversit. Therefore, previous studies of the wildlife supply-demand chain in West Africa suggest to focus on consumers to reduce wildlife exploitation. Wild meat is consumed because of a combination of behavioral factors such as beliefs, cultural traditions, and social norms. Wild meat is seen as a symbol of wealth and status, perceived as fresh, tasty and healthy, and part of people’s cultural identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are all factors that could be effectively targeted by behavioral change interventions (BCI) to reduce demand for wild meat. Rigorous evidence on the effectiveness of interventions aimed at changing consumer behavior is still lacking even though the behavioral sciences provide an ever-growing toolbox for designing BCI. For choosing the appropriate tools to design a scalable intervention in a given context it is crucial to understand underlying drivers and co-dependencies of targeted behavior. To diagnose the different contexts we will systematically employ the SES framework and the Behavioral Change Wheel (BCW) using both qualitative and quantitative approaches to design effective BCI for altering wild meat consumption and associated risk. Applying the SES and the BCW requires expertise in anthropology and behavioral sciences, but also critical reflection in an inter- and transdisciplinary team of scientists and stakeholders integrating differing knowledge systems, values, and processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The idea of the proposed project is, therefore, to study human-wildlife contact across social-ecological contexts (SEC) ranging from rural areas close to pristine habitat and degraded landscapes up to flourishing urban centers with focus on wildlife consumers and their capabilities, opportunities, motivations, and environmental contexts for identifying entry points for successful BCI to reduce the risk of zoonotic disease emergence.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Press release: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.senckenberg.de/en/pressemeldungen/funded-pandemic-prevention/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;English&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uni-marburg.de/de/aktuelles/news/2023/projekt-behavior-change&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;German&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solidarity under heterogenous adaptation costs: Experimental evidence on coping after climate hazards</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/solidarity_lab/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/solidarity_lab/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Does solidarity change in response to a fast-onset climate hazard? Evidence from Typhoon Haiyan in the Philippines</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/yolanda/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/yolanda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Standard economic theory generally assumes preferences to be stable over time. However, major events in peoples’ lives – such as natural disasters – have the potential to affect peoples’ preferences. Recently, the number of studies examining the temporal stability of individuals’ preferences increased markedly, suggesting increasing doubt about the appropriateness of this standard microeconomic assumption. This doubt is also fostered by Chuang and Schechter’ (2015) extensive literature review on the stability of preferences in general. In this survey, little attention is paid to the stability of individuals’ social preferences, which is the focus of our study. Concentrating on violent conflicts, Bauer et al. (2016) show how social preferences can be altered through such life-changing events. The focus of our study is on examining the impact of natural disasters on solidarity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Games create lasting impact</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/games_intervention/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/games_intervention/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Games as experiential learning interventions receive increasing attention. We conducted experiential learning games with 784 participants around the management of a local public good in 56 randomly selected communities in rural India. We find a significant positive impact on sustainable water management two years after the intervention compared to a control group of 27 randomly selected communities. Additional analysis indicates that achieving impact was more likely if more women were participating in the games. The results highlight the potential of experiential learning as sustainability intervention, especially when including women in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How can we overcome strategic uncertainty between providers and recipients of benefits in the the context of a shared problem?</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/insider_outsider/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/insider_outsider/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our experimental design is based on a combination of the social dilemmas studied in Blanco et al. (2018) and Gross &amp;amp; Dreu (2019). This design extends our previous studies of the insider-outsider interactions to a new social dilemma. Insiders can now choose between adaptive measures (protecting only themselves) and mitigation measures (protecting the whole group). While the group solution is the socially efficient outcome (as the outsiders do not lose their resources), insiders have incentives to invest into the individual solution to protect themselves from risk of free-riding from other insiders. Outsiders fully rely on insiders to collectively choose mitigation measures to protect them from losing their resources, as they cannot participate in any adaptation or mitigation efforts themselves. But outsiders can send transfer donations to insiders, aiming at compensating them for the efforts to invest into the group solution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Positive conservation incentives and crowding effects: a meta-analysis of lab-in-the-field experiments</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/pes_crowding_meta/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/pes_crowding_meta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Motivational crowding describes the phenomenon that external monetary incentives can undermine non-monetary, intrinsic motivations to engage in the promoted behaviour. While such crowding effects have been observed and discussed for a wide array of human behaviours (Frey and Jegen 2001; Gneezy, Meier, and Rey-Biel 2011), they have emerged as a key criticism of Payment for Ecosystem Services (PES) (Rode, Gómez-Baggethun, and Krause 2015; Akers and Yasué 2019; Ezzine-de-Blas, Corbera, and Lapeyre 2019). PES are economic incentives to land-users conditional on the provisioning of certain ecosystem services (ES), for example water regulation or carbon sequestration, or on pre-defined land-use practices that are expected to maintain or increase targeted ES (Wunder 2015). PES have been implemented worldwide in various contexts (Salzman et al. 2018), and play for example a pivotal role in agri-environmental policies in Europe and the US (Schomers and Matzdorf 2013) and have been considered a key element of REDD+ for tropical forest conservation (Angelsen et al. 2017).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>(Climate) Migrants welcome? Evidence from a Survey-Experiment in Austria </title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/migration_survey_experiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/migration_survey_experiment/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Repeated information of benefits reduce COVID-19 vaccination hesitancy: Experimental evidence from Germany</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/covid19_hesitancy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/covid19_hesitancy/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prosociality as response to slow- and fast-onset climate hazards</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/psb_cc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/psb_cc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate-related hazards increase risk aversion, place attachment and migration aspiration</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/climate_movements/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/climate_movements/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The perils of conditional payments for democracy: Experimental evidence from local leaders in rural Namibia</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/paying_for_democracy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/paying_for_democracy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Imbursement of international aid conditional on recipients applying democratic principles has been used as a policy tool to spread democratization for a long time. An obstacle that this policy faces is the capacity of recipients to manipulate elections, enabling them to receive aid without giving up power. We report results from an experiment conducted with 64 local leaders in rural Namibia that explore the effect of conditional monetary payments. Conditional payments for democracy are introduced in an environment where each leader selects among three rules for group decision-making: democratic (simple majority), pseudo-democratic (appearing democratic but keeping decision power), and dictatorial (decision by the leader). The group decision is on how to allocate resources between leaders and a set of their villagers (N=384). Leaders make rule choices over three rounds, where we gradually introduce conditional payments for adopting democratic principles, which may include adopting the pseudo-democratic rule). Our results show that without payments, 64 percent of leaders choose the democratic rule. With payments, the number of dictatorial choices decreases at the expense of an increase in pseudo-democratic choices, while the average share of democratic choices is unaffected. These average effects mask substantial heterogeneity depending on leaders’ baseline choices: one-quarter of baseline democrats switches to the pseudo-democratic or even dictatorial rule with conditional payments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When female leaders believe that men make better leaders: Empowerment in community-based water management in rural Namibia</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/leadership_norms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/leadership_norms/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The impact of terminated Payments for Ecosystem Services (IMPACTED)</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/project/impacted/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 12:06:38 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/project/impacted/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Reducing deforestation is one of the most cost-effective climate change mitigation options. Payments for Ecosystem Services (PES) are now increasingly implemented in developing countries as conservation policy tools providing conditional incentives for conservation efforts. So-called asset-building PES are based on the assumption that environmental-friendly practices are not adopted by land-users due to high initial adoption costs. PES provide incentives for a limited time period to overcome this barrier. After a successful adoption of environmental-friendly practices it is assumed that land-users will stick to them after incentives have been removed.
The proposed project will evaluate several long-term aspects of a terminated asset-building PES project in Mozambique: the Sofala community carbon project (SCCP). Between 2003 and 2013 more than 2500 smallholders were contracted to adopt various agro-forestry measures in return for cash payments. In particular, our project will build on a quasi-experimental design to evaluate the impacts of the SCCP with regard to two major criticisms concerning PES:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Environmental effectiveness with respect to deforestation and carbon sequestration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crowding-out of intrinsic pro-environmental values and social norms of smallholder farmers as well as communities’ capacities for collective action for the sustainable use of natural resources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our project includes three specific work packages. WP1 evaluates the impact of the SCCP on land-use and land-cover changes with respect to deforestation, slash-and-burn agriculture and agroforestry at the landscape level by applying remote sensing-based methods. WP2 will study and estimate below- and above-ground biomass and carbon stocks of different land-use systems in the project region, which allows us to estimate the overall impact of the SCCP on carbon stocks and sequestration. Our study thus provides one of the first long term impact assessments of an asset-building PES using both data from the air and the ground. WP3 will apply a mixed methods approach including surveys, economic experiments and participatory workshops for analysing the impact of the terminated PES on intrinsic pro-environmental conservation values, self-determination, locus-of-control, collective action and social norms at the community level. If PES crowd-out morality, introducing PES schemes may have negative consequences in other spheres of life as well. This might be especially harmful in small rural communities where pro-social behaviour is instrumental for many other non-market exchanges. Our project delivers a unique and encompassing perspective on the effects of monetary incentives on environmental conservation, human behaviour and its underlying motives in the context of a large-scale terminated PES program, which contributes to further developing a context-specific motivation crowding theory.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Procedural fairness and nepotism among local traditional and democratic leaders in rural Namibia</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/leadership/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/leadership/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are the Pacific Islands doomed to sink? The role of the media</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/post/slr/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 12:55:20 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/post/slr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I first started skimming the internet about Solomon Islands, I got the impression that this state will not exist much longer in the future. So I was very happy to have the opportunity to do research for my PhD there and for my own, in-depth view on these issues!
In mainstream media rising sea-level has become almost synonymous to climate change and global warming. The media is portraying the image of a modern day Atlantis and headlines (see figure below) are pushing the angle towards vanishing islands due to rising sea-levels.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-common-news-headlines-for-searching-pacific-islands-sea-level-rise&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ivosteimanis.github.io/img/news.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Common news headlines for searching &amp;#39;pacific islands &amp;#43;sea level rise&amp;#39;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure&amp;nbsp;&#34; data-post=&#34;:&amp;nbsp;&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
      Common news headlines for searching &amp;lsquo;pacific islands +sea level rise&amp;rsquo;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trigger for most of the above headlines and also a lot of controversy in the scientific community, was the study by Albert et al. from 2016. In this study the authors offer evidence that five Pacific islands were lost to the sea. However, the influence of climate change on these results got exaggerated by the media, as the author himself later admits. In his view, the main take-away message from the study is that &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip; these observations from the Solomons are a warning of things to come irrespective of if climate change alone caused it or a range of factors&amp;rdquo;. When reading the article by Albert et al. it becomes clear that these five islands were lost because of a combination of multiple factors; rising sea-level, wave exposure and probably also tectonic activity, and not necessarily attributed to climate change alone. Additionally, it seems that the sampling of islands is rather selective and not representative for Solomon Islands. A recent study by Kench et al (2018, see also by Mann &amp;amp; Westphal, 2014) present findings of shoreline change in all 101 islands of Tuvalu over the past four decades using the same methodology as Albert et al., but undoubtedly a more representative sample. They find that three quarters of Tuvalu&amp;rsquo;s islands have increased in size, yielding a net gain in land mass of over 70 hectare, which is nearly three percent of the total land mass of Tuvalu. Their results challenge the widespread perceptions of island loss and highlight the importance for alternative, local level adaptation strategies that embrace heterogeneity of atoll islands and their dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exacerbated representation of scientific findings as done in many news articles, might lead to two important problems. Firstly, trust in science could be undermined when readers find out later that the overstated results were not true. Most likely, they will not blame the journalist who wrote about the issue, but rather the author of the research paper and thereby lose faith in science itself. Scientists, especially in a domain with a lot of uncertainty and importance such as the impacts of climate change, should put more effort into carefully communicating their results to the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second concern is with the people living on low-lying pacific islands. In times, where internet is available even on the most remote atoll islands, access to online news is widespread. This is one channel people use to get new information about climatic changes in Solomon Islands.  People use these information to form their own expectations and perceptions about climate change. Based on my experience from a low-lying atoll formation, Reef Islands, in Solomon Islands, it seems that many people expect the worst-case scenario of inundation in the near future. They often use a &amp;ldquo;victim&amp;rdquo; narrative to explain their dependence on outsiders, such as NGOs, to help them with the consequences of climate change. This is very problematic, as climate change becomes the scapegoat for nearly every problem related to the environment and leads often to inaction. This causes a self-amplifying cycle, where people are unwilling to make investments or take actions and thereby increase their dependence on outsiders.
Thus, researchers, journalists and organizations should be careful in the way they craft and communicate messages about climate change. Spreading doomsday scenarios may affect atoll states at a larger scale by increasing dependence on the international community and hindering institutional investments into &amp;ldquo;atoll futures&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that people should not have access to better information about climate change impacts, however it is important to also deliver positive, empowering messages that encourage investments local level adaptation, continued cooperation and responsible stewardship of natural resources. After all, people have been living on these islands for thousands of years. A sea level rise of a few centimeters is unlikely to make all these islands inhabitable in the near future. However, life on these islands will become more difficult. Even more so if communities do not invest in adaption strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Albert S., Leon J. X., Grinham A. R., Church J. A., Gibbes B. R. &amp;amp; Woodroffe C. D. (2016) Interactions between sea-level rise and wave exposure on reef island dynamics in the Solomon Islands. Environmental Research Letters 11: 054011&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kench P. S., Ford M. R. &amp;amp; Owen S. D. (2018) Patterns of island change and persistence offer alternate adaptation pathways for atoll nations. Nature Communications 9: 605&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mann T. &amp;amp; Westphal H. (2014) Assessing Long-Term Changes in the Beach Width of Reef Islands Based on Temporally Fragmented Remote Sensing Data. Remote Sensing 6: 6961-6987&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Local leaders in Namibia</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/project/leadership/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 12:15:59 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/project/leadership/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Leadership structures play a key role for successful self-governance of natural resources. Leaders are responsible for drafting and enforcing rules concerning resource management and may strongly influence behavior of other resource users. The quality of leadership is also crucial for the success of decentralization reforms that have been initiated across the world in the last two decades and that are often accompanied with the creation of elected councils on the lowest level of governance responsible for managing public goods and natural resources. Decentralization and democratization reforms may improve local public good provision, but they are also prone to power abuse, nepotism, arbitrary rule enforcement, and other forms of misbehavior of leaders that may undermine trust and cooperation among community members and impede sustainable resource management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study provides experimental evidence from 32 communities in Northern Namibia on the nepotistic use of punishment and procedural fairness of local leaders. In the study area, decentralization reforms have created a coexistence of democratically legitimized leaders responsible for water management and traditional authorities, who inherit their position and have the power to allocate land to resource users. In addition, the project investigates whether leadership strategies and leaders’ personality traits have explanatory power for the real-life performance of leaders and whether local villagers’ perceptions about resource availability have an impact on the election of different types of leaders.  The results of this project contribute to the broad strands of literature on leadership, decentralization policies and common-pool resource management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study was carried out in the Ohangwena region in northern Namibia in summer 2014. In this area, the majority of inhabitants, about 80% of participants, are pastoralists who strongly depend on the availability of grazing and water resources. Access to and the management of these resources is regulated both by traditional and democratically elected leaders. The study employed three local research assistants who are native Oukwwanyama, born and raised in the study area, but currently enrolled at the University of Namibia (UNAM) in Windhoek, the capital city of Namibia. We use a combination of lab-in-the field experiments and surveys to answer our research questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is &amp;rsquo;nepotism&amp;rsquo; more prevalent under democratically legitimized or traditional forms of leadership?
Do democratically elected leaders place procedural justice before self-privileges to a larger extent than traditional leaders?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Shadow of the Future: How climate change affects human behavior</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/project/sotf/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 12:06:38 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/project/sotf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Climate change, migration of human populations, and environmental degradation are interrelated in a complex coupled human and natural system. While people have historically abandoned places with harsh conditions, the scale of these flows is expected to increase dramatically as a result of climate change. Environmental migrants are individuals forced to migrate from their home region due to sudden or long-term changes to their local environment compromising their well-being or secure livelihood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is consent among researchers that climate change will result in increasing migration and even the need to resettle entire populations. Many environmental scientists believe that the sea level will rise as a consequence of global warming and the Solomon Islands will be heavily affected by such an occurrence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “Shadow of the future” project examine, how people are likely to change their behavior in light of future climate changes, and build scenarios about potential responses, but also about their exposure to risk. The research project will identify the human reaction to severe impacts of climate change by combining an original comparative research design and the use of economic experiments, survey methods and modelling techniques. With this combination we aim to analyze how risk perception, preferences and behavior of people change with the prospect of being severely affected by climate change and whether and how the preferences translate into choices for short- and medium adaption strategies. Thus we examine the behavioral motives of potential climate refugees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our comparative design will sample people who have been affected by different degrees of sea level rise on the Solomon Islands. We sample people from low lying atolls, which are at the maximum 2m above the sea level and from higher lying islands, as well as people who already migrated from the atolls.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Influence of sea level rise on discounting, resource use and migration in small-island communities: an agent-based modelling approach</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/abm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/abm/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/admin/config.yml</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/admin/config.yml</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
