<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>conservation | Ivo Steimanis</title>
    <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/tag/conservation/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://ivosteimanis.github.io/tag/conservation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>conservation</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/media/icon_hu20ec63765a9f31cb4a6897ee299a78ea_26261_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>conservation</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/tag/conservation/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>No crowding out among those terminated from an ongoing PES program in Colombia</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/pes_termination/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/pes_termination/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Positive conservation incentives and crowding effects: a meta-analysis of lab-in-the-field experiments</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/pes_crowding_meta/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/pes_crowding_meta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Motivational crowding describes the phenomenon that external monetary incentives can undermine non-monetary, intrinsic motivations to engage in the promoted behaviour. While such crowding effects have been observed and discussed for a wide array of human behaviours (Frey and Jegen 2001; Gneezy, Meier, and Rey-Biel 2011), they have emerged as a key criticism of Payment for Ecosystem Services (PES) (Rode, Gómez-Baggethun, and Krause 2015; Akers and Yasué 2019; Ezzine-de-Blas, Corbera, and Lapeyre 2019). PES are economic incentives to land-users conditional on the provisioning of certain ecosystem services (ES), for example water regulation or carbon sequestration, or on pre-defined land-use practices that are expected to maintain or increase targeted ES (Wunder 2015). PES have been implemented worldwide in various contexts (Salzman et al. 2018), and play for example a pivotal role in agri-environmental policies in Europe and the US (Schomers and Matzdorf 2013) and have been considered a key element of REDD+ for tropical forest conservation (Angelsen et al. 2017).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
