<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Björn Vollan | Ivo Steimanis</title>
    <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/authors/bjorn-vollan/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://ivosteimanis.github.io/authors/bjorn-vollan/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Björn Vollan</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Ivo Steimanis 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/img/ivo.jpg</url>
      <title>Björn Vollan</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/authors/bjorn-vollan/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>(Climate) Migrants welcome? Evidence from a Survey-Experiment in Austria </title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/migration_survey_experiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/migration_survey_experiment/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate-related hazards increase risk aversion, place attachment and migration aspiration</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/climate_movements/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/climate_movements/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prosocial behavior in response to slow- and fast-onset hazards</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/psb_cc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/psb_cc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The perils of rewarding paying leaders for appearing democratic – Experimental evidence from Namibia</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/paying_for_democracy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/paying_for_democracy/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When female leaders believe that men make better leaders: Empowerment in community-based water management in rural Namibia</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/leadership_norms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/leadership_norms/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The impact of terminated Payments for Ecosystem Services (PES) on carbon stocks, deforestation, collective action and intrinsic motivations for conservation.</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/project/impacted/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 12:06:38 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/project/impacted/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Reducing deforestation is one of the most cost-effective climate change mitigation options. Payments for Ecosystem Services (PES) are now increasingly implemented in developing countries as conservation policy tools providing conditional incentives for conservation efforts. So-called asset-building PES are based on the assumption that environmental-friendly practices are not adopted by land-users due to high initial adoption costs. PES provide incentives for a limited time period to overcome this barrier. After a successful adoption of environmental-friendly practices it is assumed that land-users will stick to them after incentives have been removed. 
The proposed project will evaluate several long-term aspects of a terminated asset-building PES project in Mozambique: the Sofala community carbon project (SCCP). Between 2003 and 2013 more than 2500 smallholders were contracted to adopt various agro-forestry measures in return for cash payments. In particular, our project will build on a quasi-experimental design to evaluate the impacts of the SCCP with regard to two major criticisms concerning PES:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Environmental effectiveness with respect to deforestation and carbon sequestration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crowding-out of intrinsic pro-environmental values and social norms of smallholder farmers as well as communities’ capacities for collective action for the sustainable use of natural resources.
Our project includes three specific work packages. WP1 evaluates the impact of the SCCP on land-use and land-cover changes with respect to deforestation, slash-and-burn agriculture and agroforestry at the landscape level by applying remote sensing-based methods. WP2 will study and estimate below- and above-ground biomass and carbon stocks of different land-use systems in the project region, which allows us to estimate the overall impact of the SCCP on carbon stocks and sequestration. Our study thus provides one of the first long term impact assessments of an asset-building PES using both data from the air and the ground. WP3 will apply a mixed methods approach including surveys, economic experiments and participatory workshops for analysing the impact of the terminated PES on intrinsic pro-environmental conservation values, self-determination, locus-of-control, collective action and social norms at the community level. If PES crowd-out morality, introducing PES schemes may have negative consequences in other spheres of life as well. This might be especially harmful in small rural communities where pro-social behaviour is instrumental for many other non-market exchanges. Our project delivers a unique and encompassing perspective on the effects of monetary incentives on environmental conservation, human behaviour and its underlying motives in the context of a large-scale terminated PES program, which contributes to further developing a context-specific motivation crowding theory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Procedural fairness and nepotism among local traditional and democratic leaders in rural Namibia</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/leadership/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/leadership/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Local leaders in Namibia</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/project/leadership/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 12:15:59 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/project/leadership/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Leadership structures play a key role for successful self-governance of natural resources. Leaders are responsible for drafting and enforcing rules concerning resource management and may strongly influence behavior of other resource users. The quality of leadership is also crucial for the success of decentralization reforms that have been initiated across the world in the last two decades and that are often accompanied with the creation of elected councils on the lowest level of governance responsible for managing public goods and natural resources. Decentralization and democratization reforms may improve local public good provision, but they are also prone to power abuse, nepotism, arbitrary rule enforcement, and other forms of misbehavior of leaders that may undermine trust and cooperation among community members and impede sustainable resource management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study provides experimental evidence from 32 communities in Northern Namibia on the nepotistic use of punishment and procedural fairness of local leaders. In the study area, decentralization reforms have created a coexistence of democratically legitimized leaders responsible for water management and traditional authorities, who inherit their position and have the power to allocate land to resource users. In addition, the project investigates whether leadership strategies and leaders’ personality traits have explanatory power for the real-life performance of leaders and whether local villagers’ perceptions about resource availability have an impact on the election of different types of leaders.  The results of this project contribute to the broad strands of literature on leadership, decentralization policies and common-pool resource management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study was carried out in the Ohangwena region in northern Namibia in summer 2014. In this area, the majority of inhabitants, about 80% of participants, are pastoralists who strongly depend on the availability of grazing and water resources. Access to and the management of these resources is regulated both by traditional and democratically elected leaders. The study employed three local research assistants who are native Oukwwanyama, born and raised in the study area, but currently enrolled at the University of Namibia (UNAM) in Windhoek, the capital city of Namibia. We use a combination of lab-in-the field experiments and surveys to answer our research questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is &amp;lsquo;nepotism&amp;rsquo; more prevalent under democratically legitimized or traditional forms of leadership?
Do democratically elected leaders place procedural justice before self-privileges to a larger extent than traditional leaders?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Shadow of the Future: How climate change affects human behavior</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/project/sotf/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 12:06:38 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/project/sotf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Climate change, migration of human populations, and environmental degradation are interrelated in a complex coupled human and natural system. While people have historically abandoned places with harsh conditions, the scale of these flows is expected to increase dramatically as a result of climate change. Environmental migrants are individuals forced to migrate from their home region due to sudden or long-term changes to their local environment compromising their well-being or secure livelihood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is consent among researchers that climate change will result in increasing migration and even the need to resettle entire populations. Many environmental scientists believe that the sea level will rise as a consequence of global warming and the Solomon Islands will be heavily affected by such an occurrence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “Shadow of the future” project examine, how people are likely to change their behavior in light of future climate changes, and build scenarios about potential responses, but also about their exposure to risk. The research project will identify the human reaction to severe impacts of climate change by combining an original comparative research design and the use of economic experiments, survey methods and modelling techniques. With this combination we aim to analyze how risk perception, preferences and behavior of people change with the prospect of being severely affected by climate change and whether and how the preferences translate into choices for short- and medium adaption strategies. Thus we examine the behavioral motives of potential climate refugees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our comparative design will sample people who have been affected by different degrees of sea level rise on the Solomon Islands. We sample people from low lying atolls, which are at the maximum 2m above the sea level and from higher lying islands, as well as people who already migrated from the atolls.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Influence of sea level rise on discounting, resource use and migration in small-island communities: an agent-based modelling approach</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/abm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/publication/abm/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
