<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Work in progress | Ivo Steimanis</title>
    <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Work in progress</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/media/icon_hu20ec63765a9f31cb4a6897ee299a78ea_26261_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Work in progress</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Does solidarity change in response to a fast-onset climate hazard? Evidence from Typhoon Haiyan in the Philippines</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/yolanda/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/yolanda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Standard economic theory generally assumes preferences to be stable over time. However, major events in peoples’ lives – such as natural disasters – have the potential to affect peoples’ preferences. Recently, the number of studies examining the temporal stability of individuals’ preferences increased markedly, suggesting increasing doubt about the appropriateness of this standard microeconomic assumption. This doubt is also fostered by Chuang and Schechter’ (2015) extensive literature review on the stability of preferences in general. In this survey, little attention is paid to the stability of individuals’ social preferences, which is the focus of our study. Concentrating on violent conflicts, Bauer et al. (2016) show how social preferences can be altered through such life-changing events. The focus of our study is on examining the impact of natural disasters on solidarity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Games create lasting impact</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/games_intervention/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/games_intervention/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Games as experiential learning interventions receive increasing attention. We conducted experiential learning games with 784 participants around the management of a local public good in 56 randomly selected communities in rural India. We find a significant positive impact on sustainable water management two years after the intervention compared to a control group of 27 randomly selected communities. Additional analysis indicates that achieving impact was more likely if more women were participating in the games. The results highlight the potential of experiential learning as sustainability intervention, especially when including women in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How can we overcome strategic uncertainty between providers and recipients of benefits in the the context of a shared problem?</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/insider_outsider/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/insider_outsider/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our experimental design is based on a combination of the social dilemmas studied in Blanco et al. (2018) and Gross &amp;amp; Dreu (2019). This design extends our previous studies of the insider-outsider interactions to a new social dilemma. Insiders can now choose between adaptive measures (protecting only themselves) and mitigation measures (protecting the whole group). While the group solution is the socially efficient outcome (as the outsiders do not lose their resources), insiders have incentives to invest into the individual solution to protect themselves from risk of free-riding from other insiders. Outsiders fully rely on insiders to collectively choose mitigation measures to protect them from losing their resources, as they cannot participate in any adaptation or mitigation efforts themselves. But outsiders can send transfer donations to insiders, aiming at compensating them for the efforts to invest into the group solution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Positive conservation incentives and crowding effects: a meta-analysis of lab-in-the-field experiments</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/pes_crowding_meta/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/pes_crowding_meta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Motivational crowding describes the phenomenon that external monetary incentives can undermine non-monetary, intrinsic motivations to engage in the promoted behaviour. While such crowding effects have been observed and discussed for a wide array of human behaviours (Frey and Jegen 2001; Gneezy, Meier, and Rey-Biel 2011), they have emerged as a key criticism of Payment for Ecosystem Services (PES) (Rode, Gómez-Baggethun, and Krause 2015; Akers and Yasué 2019; Ezzine-de-Blas, Corbera, and Lapeyre 2019). PES are economic incentives to land-users conditional on the provisioning of certain ecosystem services (ES), for example water regulation or carbon sequestration, or on pre-defined land-use practices that are expected to maintain or increase targeted ES (Wunder 2015). PES have been implemented worldwide in various contexts (Salzman et al. 2018), and play for example a pivotal role in agri-environmental policies in Europe and the US (Schomers and Matzdorf 2013) and have been considered a key element of REDD+ for tropical forest conservation (Angelsen et al. 2017).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The perils of conditional payments for democracy: Experimental evidence from local leaders in rural Namibia</title>
      <link>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/paying_for_democracy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivosteimanis.github.io/workingpapers/paying_for_democracy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Imbursement of international aid conditional on recipients applying democratic principles has been used as a policy tool to spread democratization for a long time. An obstacle that this policy faces is the capacity of recipients to manipulate elections, enabling them to receive aid without giving up power. We report results from an experiment conducted with 64 local leaders in rural Namibia that explore the effect of conditional monetary payments. Conditional payments for democracy are introduced in an environment where each leader selects among three rules for group decision-making: democratic (simple majority), pseudo-democratic (appearing democratic but keeping decision power), and dictatorial (decision by the leader). The group decision is on how to allocate resources between leaders and a set of their villagers (N=384). Leaders make rule choices over three rounds, where we gradually introduce conditional payments for adopting democratic principles, which may include adopting the pseudo-democratic rule). Our results show that without payments, 64 percent of leaders choose the democratic rule. With payments, the number of dictatorial choices decreases at the expense of an increase in pseudo-democratic choices, while the average share of democratic choices is unaffected. These average effects mask substantial heterogeneity depending on leaders’ baseline choices: one-quarter of baseline democrats switches to the pseudo-democratic or even dictatorial rule with conditional payments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
